RG 069:148, John J. McMahon Papers
Connecticut State Library
John J. McMahon papers
1901-1954
bulk 1925-1926
Connecticut State Library
McMahon, John J.
1.75 cubic feet
John J. McMahon was born in Hartford on April 22, 1875. He served as a volunteer in the First Regiment Infantry Connecticut National Guard, the Spanish-American War, and retired as a Colonel from the Connecticut National Guard on November 23, 1931. He was an officer and member in the First Connecticut Volunteer Infantry Veteran Association, Spanish-American War - 1898 and the Department of Connecticut United Spanish War Veterans. McMahon was elected to the Hartford Board of Education from 1911-1916, elected City Alderman from Hartford's seventh ward from 1922-1926, and worked as an architect in Hartford from 1893-1958.
RG069_148
2009-031
Biographical Note
John Joseph McMahon was born in Hartford on April 22, 1875. He attended St. Patrick's School. In 1890, a few months before graduation, he left school and started working. The next three years he worked as an errand boy for a Hartford clothing shop. In 1893 he was brought on as an apprentice under architect Frederick Royal Comstock working both in Hartford and New York City.
Military Service
McMahon's apprentice work with Comstock ended when he was called to serve in the Spanish-American War in 1898. He enlisted before the war as a Private in the Connecticut National Guard, 1st Connecticut Infantry, Company B on April 1, 1895. He was promoted to the rank of Corporal on December 8, 1896, to Sergeant on December 7, 1897, and to 1st Sergeant on May 12, 1898.
The U.S.S. Maine on the night of February 15, 1898 exploded and sank while anchored in Spain controlled Havana harbor, Cuba. The exact cause of the explosion remains a mystery. The sinking of the Maine, along with other events, pushed the United States towards war with Spain. The United States issued a declaration of war against Spain on April 25, 1898. McMahon was mustered into United States Service on May 17, 1898.
McMahon served in Company B, First Regiment Connecticut Volunteer Infantry, Connecticut National Guard during the Spanish-American War. The First Regiment Connecticut Volunteer Infantry was assigned coastal defense duty during the war. Company B was transported by the Steamer Manhansett from Crescent Beach near Niantic to Great Gull Island, New York on June 8, 1898. The men pitched camp in an area 175 feet long by 40 feet wide as the rest of the island was being excavated for Fort Michie. On July 18, 1898 the First Regiment Connecticut Volunteer Infantry was ordered to Camp Alger, near Dunn Loring, Virginia.
Company B of the First Regiment Connecticut Volunteer Infantry was mustered out of United States Service on October 31, 1898. McMahon was honorably discharged on June 16, 1899 as a 1st Sergeant and re-enlisted as a Private with Company B on November 29, 1901. He was promoted to the following ranks in Company B, First Regiment, Connecticut National Guard: Corporal on October 1, 1902; 2nd Lieutenant on March 31, 1903; 1st Lieutenant on November 24, 1903; Captain on February 17, 1908; and Major on March 25, 1909. The First Connecticut Infantry, Connecticut National Guard was called back into United State Service on June 20, 1916 for duty on the Mexican border at Nogales, Arizona. Major McMahon commanded the 1st Battalion of the First Connecticut Infantry. The regiment was mustered out of United States Service on October 30, 1916. He transferred to the Connecticut National Guard Reserve on December 6, 1916.
McMahon was appointed Lieutenant Colonel in the First Regiment Infantry Connecticut State Guard on March 29, 1917. He resigned from the Connecticut State Guard on October 24, 1918. On October 25, 1918 McMahon was appointed Major, Quartermaster Corps, United States Army. He served as Chief of Plant Protection, Maintenance and Repair Division, Philadelphia Supply Depot. McMahon was honorably discharged on January 18, 1919. He was appointed a Major in the Quartermaster Reserve Corps (Q.M.R.C.) on March 11, 1919 and reappointed Major on March 11, 1924 to March 10, 1929. Governor Wilbur L. Cross commissioned McMahon a Colonel, Infantry, Connecticut National Guard on November 23, 1931. John J. McMahon retired as a Colonel in the Connecticut National Guard on November 23, 1931.
Veteran Association Member and Officer
John J. McMahon was a member of the First Connecticut Volunteer Infantry Veteran Association, Spanish-American War - 1898. He was Secretary of the association from 1952-1954. McMahon was a member of the Department of Connecticut United Spanish War Veterans. He served as Adjutant of the department from 1925 to 1926. He was a member of the United Spanish War Veterans, Charles L. Burdett Camp No. 4 of Hartford.
Architect Career
After serving in the Spanish-American War McMahon returned to being an architect. He was a draftsman and associate architect in the Hartford firm of John J. Dwyer, later Dwyer & McMahon, from 1900-1911. During his time with Dwyer he helped design at least six different buildings including: St. Augustine's Church at Barry Square; St. Michael's Church; House of Good Shepherd; St. Elizabeth's House; First Administration Building for St. Francis Hospital; and the Elks Club Lodge. On October 24, 1911 Dwyer passed away. McMahon, along with Dwyer & McMahon draftsman Frank Warren Whiton, formed the architectural firm of Whiton & McMahon. The firm designed over twenty buildings in Hartford and surrounding towns including: Mount St. Joseph's Academy; City of Hartford Fire Station #3; Washington Street School Additions; Corning Building at Main Street and Asylum Street; and many other buildings. In June of 1932 McMahon and Whiton dissolved there partnership. McMahon spent the next 26 years as an independent architect designing buildings in greater Hartford. He did partner once while independent to design St. Lawrence O'Toole Church with architect Russell Hills.1
Civic Leadership
John J. McMahon was elected to the Hartford Board of Education from 1911 to 1916. McMahon, a Democrat, was elected City Alderman from Hartford's seventh ward in 1922 and served until 1926. He served on the City Board of Finance from 1925 to 1926. He was active with the Elks Club and served as a trustee of St. Augustine's Church. John J. McMahon died in Hartford on September 8, 1958 at the age of 83.
Endnotes
1 Joseph McMahon, "A Grandfather's Contribution to Hartford's Unique Architectural Landscape," Hartford Preservation Alliance Newsletter (Summer 2007): 3.
Scope and Content
The papers were arranged into four series and three subseries which reflect John J. McMahon's personal life, military service, and membership in veteran associations in Connecticut. The series include Personal Papers, First Connecticut Volunteer Infantry Veteran Association, Spanish-American War - 1898, Department of Connecticut United Spanish War Veterans, and Photographs. The subseries under the Department of Connecticut United Spanish War Veterans series include Correspondence with Camps, Office Files, and General Orders.
Series 1. Personal Papers, 1901-1954, includes biographical information, clippings, correspondence, national guard correspondence and orders, First Regiment Infantry history and Company B by-laws.
Series 2. First Connecticut Volunteer Infantry Veteran Association, Spanish-American War - 1898, 1949-1954, consists of correspondence, reports of deaths, financial report, and rosters.
Series 3. Department of Connecticut United Spanish War Veterans, 1925-1926, contains correspondence, financial records, minutes, and rosters. The miscellaneous folder contains two pages from a book with the photograph of Company C and correspondence between a Mr. Beck and Albert Hart. The correspondence with the camps consists of letters between the various camps and department. The general orders contain printed orders from other state's departments of the United Spanish War Veterans and the national headquarters.
Series 4. Photographs, undated, contains a panorama photograph of a United States outpost along the border with Mexico.
Arrangement
Series 1. Personal Papers, 1901-1954
Series 2. First Connecticut Volunteer Infantry Veteran Association, Spanish-American War - 1898, 1949-1954
Series 3. Department of Connecticut United Spanish War Veterans, 1925-1926
Series 4. Photographs, undated
Related Material
, Connecticut State Library.
The John J. McMahon architecture notes, located at the Connecticut Historical Society, document McMahon's career as an architect.
Bibliography
Books
Connecticut Adjutant-General's Office. Record of Service of Connecticut Men in the Army, Navy, and Marine Corps of the United States in the Spanish-American War, Philippine Insurrection and China Relief Expedition, From April 2, 1898 to July 4, 1904. Hartford: Case, Lockwood & Brainard Company, 1919.
Keller, Allan. The Spanish-American War: A Compact History. New York: Hawthorn Books, Inc., 1969.
Traxel, David. 1898: The Birth of the American Century. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1998.
United States. Army. Connecticut Infantry Regiment, 1st (1898). First Regiment, Connecticut National Guard. 1898-1899. Official History. Outline History of the Regiment During the Spanish-American War as First Connecticut Infantry, U.S. Volunteers. Hartford: City Printing Company, 1900.
Articles
McMahon, Joseph. " " Hartford Preservation Alliance Newsletter (Summer 2007): 3.
Newspapers
Hartford Courant, 1875-1970.
Websites
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Organizations:
United Spanish War Veterans. Dept. of Connecticut
Subjects:
United Spanish War Veterans. Dept. of Connecticut -- Records and correspondence; Spanish-American War, 1898 -- Connecticut -- Societies, etc.; Connecticut. National Guard--History; United Spanish War Veterans; United States Army. Connecticut Infantry Regiment, 1st (1898); Connecticut -- History, Military
Places:
Hartford (Conn.)
Persons:
McMahon, John J., 1875-1958; Ross, Herbert A.; Shea, Frank E.
Document Types:
Clippings; Correspondence; Financial records; Minutes; Pamphlets; Panoramas; Photographs; Publications; Reports; Rosters
Restrictions on Access
See the policy.
Provenance
The John J. McMahon papers were donated by James McMahon to the State Library in 2008.
Container List
- Series 1. Personal Papers, 1901-1954
  - Biographical file, circa 1919-1925, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - By-Laws Company B, First Regiment, Connecticut National Guard, 1901 October 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1944 January 6 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, circa 1916 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - Connecticut National Guard, 1916-1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - First Regiment Infantry Connecticut National Guard, Thirteenth Regiment Heavy Artillery National Guard New York, circa 1906; photocopies (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Military Order of the Carabao, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series 2. First Connecticut Volunteer Infantry Veteran Association, Spanish-American War - 1898, 1949-1954
  - Correspondence - miscellaneous, 1952-1954, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - Ross, Herbert A., 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Deaths reported at reunions, circa 1949-1952 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Financial report of secretary, 55th anniversary reunion at Saengerbund Club, 1953 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Rosters, 1949 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series 3. Department of Connecticut United Spanish War Veterans, 1925-1926
  - Correspondence - Commander Frank E. Shea, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence - McMahon, John, circa 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Financial records, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - An Invitation to United Spanish War Veterans to Stop Over in the "Gate City of the South," Atlanta, Georgia, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - McCaskey Camp News, "Independence Day Number," Lancaster, Pennsylvania, 1925 July (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Minutes of the Twenty-Third Annual Encampment, 1926 June 11-12 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1925-1926, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Roster - corrected, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence with Camps, 1925-1926
    - Allan Osborn Camp No. 1, New Haven, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Charles B. Bowen Camp No. 2, Meriden, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Lieut. N.W. Bishop Camp No. 3, Bridgeport, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Charles L. Burdett Camp No. 4, Hartford, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - A.G. Hammond Camp No. 5, New Britain, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - R.S. Griswold Camp No. 6, Norwich, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - George M. Cole Camp No. 7, New London, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - A.C. Tyler Camp No. 8, Willimantic, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - William McKinley Camp No. 9, Norwalk, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Sidney Beach Camp No. 10, Bridgeport, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Emerson H. Liscum Camp No. 12, Waterbury, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Ward Cheney Camp No. 13, Manchester, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - James W. Milne Camp No. 14, Rockville, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Frederick A. Hill Camp No. 15, Stamford, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Charles P. Kirkland Camp No. 18, Winsted, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - W.S. Steele Camp No. 19, Torrington, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - William H. Hamilton Camp No. 20, Danielson, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - G.A. Hadsell Camp No. 21, Bristol, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Milford Camp No. 22, Milford, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - John M. Handley Camp No. 23, Thompsonville, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Frederick Fuller Camp No. 24, Guilford, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Nelson A. Miles Camp No. 25, Middletown, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Ernest Weichert Camp No. 26, Danbury, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Oliver J. Carey Camp No. 27, Stafford Springs, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Gen. Joseph Wheeler Camp No. 28, Derby, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - A. Wilder Merriam Camp No. 29, Putnam, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Office Files, 1925-1926
    - Camp orders, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence - Adjutant General, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence - Adjutant and Quartermaster, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence - Auxiliary, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence - Chaplain, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence - Chief-of-Staff, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence - Commander-In-Chief, Thompson, Carmai, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence - Historian, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence - Inspector, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence - Judge Advocate, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence - Junior Vice-Commander, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence - Marshall, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence - Military Order of the Serpent, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, circa 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 34-35)
    - Correspondence - Past Commanders and Other Past Department Officers, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence - Patriotic Inspectors, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence - Senior Vice-Commander, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence - Soldiers' Hospital Board, 1925-1926 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence - Surgeon, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General Orders, 1925-1926
    - Department of Arizona, 1925 October 15 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Department of Arkansas, 1925-1926 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Department of Connecticut, Auxiliary, 1925-1926 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Department of the District of Columbia, 1925-1926 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Department of Florida, 1925-1926 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Department of Illinois, 1925-1926 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Department of Indiana, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Department of Iowa, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Department of Kansas, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Department of Kentucky, 1925-1926 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Department of Louisiana, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Department of Louisiana, Auxiliary, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Department of Massachusetts, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Department of Minnesota, 1925 December 15 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Department of Montana, 1925 December 2 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Department of Nebraska, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Department of New Hampshire, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Department of New Jersey, 1926 January 1 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Department of New York, 1925-1926 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Department of Oregon, 1925-1926 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Department of Potomac, 1925 January 15 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Department of Rhode Island, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Department of Texas, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Department of West Virginia, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - National Headquarters, Cleveland, Ohio, 1925-1926 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - National Headquarters, Washington, D.C., 1925-1926 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Series 4. Photographs, undated
  - View from one of the U.S.A. Outposts, Mexican Border, undated; panorama (Box 4)